Alexandre Rothen papers, Rockefeller University Faculty, Ingests, 1983 and 1988 FA989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Alexandre Rothen papers, Rockefeller University Faculty, Ingests, 1983 and 1988
1932-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rothen, Alexandre
FA989
8.8 Cubic Feet 11 boxes.
11 boxes.
Biographical / Historical
Alexandre Rothen, physical chemist at The Rockefeller University (formerly The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research) from 1927-1970. He built one of the first Polariscopes for the study of rotatory dispersion in the ultraviolet range and developed the air-driven centrifuge (originally designed by Pickels of the Rockefeller Foundation). From 1942 he was interested in monomolecular layers and published many papers on chemical interactions at a liquid-solid interface. He built the first ellipsometer with a half shadow device.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University. Laboratory notebooks are restricted for 40 years from the date of reception. Laboratory notebooks are open for research in 2028. Brittle or damaged materials are open at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Boxes 1-7: received from T.P. King, December 1983.
Boxes 8-11: received from Mrs. Rothen, October 1988.
File Plan
Former Classification: I 450 R743-U
Other Finding Aids
FA193 Alexandre Rothen papers, Rockefeller University Faculty.
Scope and Contents
Contains papers, reprints, scientific slides and illustrations, laboratory notebooks and other associated research materials.
- Reprints, 1932-1966 (Box 1)
- Reprints, 1967-1982 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous scientific papers (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous scientific papers (Box 3)
- Negatives (scientific illustrations) (Box 4)
- Negatives (scientific illustrations) (Box 5)
- Glass slides (scientific) (Box 6)
- Glass slides (scientific) (Box 7)
- Reprints, 1940-1975; 3 binders.
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1940s (Box 8)
  Scope and Contents
  Rothen and lab assistants.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted - Open in 2028.
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1950-1956 (Box 9)
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1956-1970 (Box 10)
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1969-1974 (Box 11)
  Lab assistants.